<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The wise King, and the learned iudge in a sermon, out of the 10. verse of the 2. psalme: lamenting the death, and proposing the example, of Sir Edvvard Levvenor, a religious gentleman. Preached vpon a lecture-day at Canham in Suffolke. By Bezalell Carter.</title>
            <author>Carter, Bezaleel, d. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853838</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18050)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1061:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The wise King, and the learned iudge in a sermon, out of the 10. verse of the 2. psalme: lamenting the death, and proposing the example, of Sir Edvvard Levvenor, a religious gentleman. Preached vpon a lecture-day at Canham in Suffolke. By Bezalell Carter.</title>
                  <author>Carter, Bezaleel, d. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 68, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by C. L[eege] 1618. And are to be sold by Matthevv Lavv in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Foxe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1618]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; last leaf torn, affecting top margin, pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19236:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19236:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19236:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19236:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Right <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull and godly Ladie, the Lady</hi> LEVVKENOR of <hi>Denham, Grace and Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ELect Ladie, it was the ſaying of <hi>Dauid, The righteous ſhall bee had in euerlaſting remembrance,</hi> Pſal. 112. 6. and of <hi>Salomon, That the memoriall of the iuſt ſhall bee bleſſed,</hi> Prou. 10. 7. Theſe two Scriptures haue much encouraged me, to penne and print this Sermon following; and your entire loue to your louing husband departed, hath emboldened me (with hope of accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to preſent it to your Ladie-ſhip, as a picture at all times to put you in mind of his godly life and conuerſation, that in theſe perilous and luke-warm times, when zeale growes cold, and fewe or none labour to draw on others, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage others to runne the wayes of Gods commandements, when you ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:19236:3"/> at any time behold this picture, you may be prouoked and ſtirred vp (as you haue begunne well) ſo to perſeuere and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede on, and grow more and more in grace. The eternall God of heauen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you, euen as he hath afflicted you, and that God crowne both you and yours with his beſt bleſſings. So prayes ſtill,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips in all dutie bounden B. C.</signed>
               <dateline>Canham, <date>Octob. 24. 1618.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19236:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> And to the Right <hi>Worſhipfull &amp; religious Gentleman, Sir</hi> ROBERT LEVVKENOR, of <hi>Acris</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> to Miſtris GOVRNY of great Ellingham, <hi>to Miſtris</hi> STEVVARD, and Miſtris CATLIN of <hi>Denham,</hi> Grace and Peace.</head>
            <p>RIght Worſhipfull, after I had prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched this Sermon, I conferred with ſome of my brethren about the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of it, and ſome aduiſed me to print it, others to conceale it for two cauſes: Firſt, becauſe the world is full of bookes: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe it would make me lyable to many cenſures and imputations.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, I anſwer, that the world is full of bookes, but that it is too full of godly bookes, I could neuer heare it prooued. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I know that I ſhall bewray mine own weakenes exceedingly, and expoſe my ſelfe to many hard cenſures, by publiſhing this Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet; and yet for all that, I chooſe rather to
<pb facs="tcp:19236:4"/> be hated, to make my ſelfe a by-word, and a reproach, then to neglect any courſe that may turn to the good, though but of one ſoule; yea, and if it ſhould turne to the good of none, yet ſhall I ſing but to the ſame tune that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Gods ſeruants haue done before me: <hi>I haue laboured in vaine, and ſpent my ſtrength to no purpoſe, Iſa. 49. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer I haue done, I haue made bold alſo to preſent it to your Worſhips, as a teſtimonie of my thankefulnes vnto you all, and a meanes to reuiue and continue, (as much as in me lies) the deſerued memorie of your godly brother, whome from my ſoule I loued in his life, and from my ſoule deſire to honour in his death. If this poore mite may be accepted of you, and profitable to Gods Church, I haue my deſire: which that it may be, I haue praied: and ſo praies ſtill,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A poore, but a zealous welwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to your whole ſtocke and familie, BEZAL. CARTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19236:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALM. 2. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Be wiſe now therefore O yee Kings: bee learned, O yee Iudges of the earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalme was pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Dauid:</hi> witnes, Act. 4. 25. <hi>Which by the mouth of thy ſeruant Dauid haſt ſaid, Why did the Gentiles rage, &amp;c.</hi> The principall matter contained in it, is Chriſt and his Kingdome, as you may perceiue if you read, Act. 4. 25. and Act. 13. 33. and Hebr. 1. 5. for here <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> as in many other things, is a type of Chriſt: and though all this Pſalme may be applyed to <hi>Dauid,</hi> and his kingdom; yet notwithſtanding it may be applyed alſo to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Kingdome: and the ſpirit of God would teach vs, that as <hi>Dauid</hi> raigned and ruled in Zion, and ſubdued his enemies, euen ſo ſhould <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19236:5"/> Chriſt</hi> raigne, and beare rule in his Church, euen in deſpight of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches enemies. And whoſoeuer reads the whole Pſalme muſt needs ſee,</p>
            <p>Firſt, what oppoſition was made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kingdome of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſequel and conſequent vpon the oppoſition made.</p>
            <p>Their oppoſition was vniuerſall, Kings and Commons; Princes, Peeres, and People; Iewes and Gentiles. The Kings and Princes raged, the Iewes, the heathens, and all people murmured, and all to no purpoſe: for he that ſate in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen laughed at them, and by their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion they expoſed themſelues to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding perill and danger. For firſt, in oppoſing Chriſt, they oppoſed God the Father alſo, that gaue this authority vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Son, and made him the ruler and gouernour of his people; <hi>I</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>haue placed my King vpon Zion mine holy mountaine, &amp;c. I will declare the decree, &amp;c. Hee that dwells in heauen ſhall laugh them to ſcorne, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is further amplified in regard of God the Sonne, that is alſo euerie way furniſhed with ſufficiencie of power,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19236:5"/> both for the defence of his Church, and the finall ouerthrowe and confuſion of his enemies; and is therefore compared to ſome mightie gyant, with a mace or yron ſcepter in his hand; and Kings, &amp; Princes, and all nations are reſembled vnto potters pots: and it ſhould bee no more with Chriſt to ouerthrowe and cruſh them in peices, then it would haue been for <hi>Goliah</hi> with his maſſie ſpeare, whoſe ſhaft was like a weauers beame, to haue broken an earthen veſſell in pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But of theſe things I haue ſpoken before; now mark and obſerue how one thing depends vpon another. Kings and Princes make oppoſition againſt Chriſt and his Kingdome; God the Father hee ſits in heauen and laughes at them, and vexes them with grieuous iudgements; God the Sonne, he ſtands like a mighty gyant, with a mace of yron in his hand, ready to ſtrike and quaſh them in pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and then it followes, <hi>Bee wiſe nowe therefore, O yee Kings: be learned, O yee Iudges, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the words themſelues, note in them theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a double exhortation: 1. To
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19236:6"/> wiſedome: 2. To learning.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the circumſtances expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:<note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> 1. Of the time, and that is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>now.</hi> 2. Of the perſons: 1. Kings: 2. Iudges: <hi>Be wiſe now therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For our better proceeding, it would be enquired, what he meanes, by <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and <hi>learning.</hi> And,<note place="margin">Be wiſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>wiſedome,</hi> he meanes not here a carnall or worldly wiſedome, ſuch an one as <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaks of, and calls it <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſenſuall, &amp; deuilliſh,</hi> chap. 3. 15. when men are wiſe to take vengeance vpon their enemies, to hoard vp wealth, to manage their affaires to their beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: for this wiſedome is not wanting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the men of the world, that are wiſe enough to <hi>diſcerne the face of the skie, and the ſignes of the times,</hi> Matth. 16. 2. and wiſe enough to make a ſmall <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phah,</hi> and a great <hi>Shekle,</hi> and a <hi>falſe bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance,</hi> Amos, 8. 5. and generally the men of the world are wiſe in <hi>their generation,</hi> Luk. 16. 8. But the ſpirit of God in this place ſpeaks of a <hi>ſpiritual &amp; heauenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi> of which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes, Pſal. 119. 8. <hi>The wiſedome of the prudent, is to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the way of the Lord: but the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19236:6"/> of the foole is deceipt:</hi> and this <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> was that which <hi>Salomon</hi> prayed for, and did obtaine of God, 1. King. 3. 9. This is that which <hi>Iames</hi> calleth the <hi>wiſedome from aboue,</hi> Iam. 3. 7. This is that which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of, when <hi>men are wiſe to ſaluation,</hi> 2. Tim. 3. 15. In a word, let that notable place, Deut. 4. 5. ſuffice for the defining of <hi>true wiſedome: Behold,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes, I haue taught you ſtatutes, and iudgements, as the Lord hath commanded me: keepe therefore, and doe them: for this is your wiſedome and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi> So as he that knowes his duty to God, and doth it, he is a <hi>wiſe man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the more familiar handling of this Doctrine, and the further confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of it, conſider we by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, who is a <hi>wiſe man,</hi> and what <hi>wiſedome</hi> is.</p>
            <p>Two things here are which makes men to be accounted wiſe: 1. Sight. 2. Foreſight.</p>
            <p>Firſt ſight, when men are able to iudge of things.</p>
            <p>Secondly, foreſight, when men are wiſe to foreſee dangers, as alſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for time to come.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19236:7"/>
            <p>Firſt, he is accounted <hi>wiſe,</hi> that is skilfull to diſcerne of things that differ one from another; and when he hath the proffer both of good and mixe wares, is skilfull enough to preſerue himſelfe from couſenage.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we count him <hi>wiſe,</hi> that is wiſe to preuent dangers: <hi>The wiſe man hath eyes in his head, but the foole walkes in darkeneſſe,</hi> Eccleſ. 2. 4. <hi>Salomon</hi> reſembles fooles to blind men, or men that walke in the darke, that foreſee no perills: and compares wiſe men to thoſe which walke at high-noone and foreſee euery inconuenience; <hi>a prudent man ſees the plague and hides himſelfe, but fooles goe on, and are puniſhed.</hi> Pro. 22. 3.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, hee is alſo accounted <hi>wiſe,</hi> that is wiſe to prouide and lay vp for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture time; and thus the vniuſt <hi>Steward</hi> is commended, becauſe he prouided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time that his maſter ſhould diſcharge him of his office: for ſo the text ſaith, that the <hi>Lord commended the vniuſt ſteward, becauſe he had done wiſely,</hi> Luk. 16. 8.</p>
            <p>The aſſumption to be gathered from all that hath been ſaid is onely this,</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19236:7"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>1</label> That onely <hi>regenerate</hi> men are <hi>wiſe,</hi>and all <hi>vnregenerate</hi> men no better then fooles.</q>
            <p>Firſt, regenerate men are only wiſe to iudge, and <hi>chooſe the better part with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Luk. 10. 42.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they only <hi>foreſee the plague, and auoid it;</hi> Pro. 27. 12.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they onely <hi>lay vp treaſures for time to come euen in heauen,</hi> Matth. 6. 20. and therefore they onely are wiſe.</p>
            <p>As for the vnregenerate. Firſt, they want iudgement. Whereto may we better reſemble them, then to little children, that are more deſirous of toies and trifles, of apples and babies, then of lands and inheritances. To whom may we liken them better then to profane <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> that eſteemed more of a portion of meat, then of his birthright, Heb. 12. 16. Would we not brand him for an ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot, which would chooſe braſſe rather then gold, flint ſtones before precious ſtones, chaffe before corne? and yet thouſands there are in the world, yea and counted wiſe men, that are more fooliſh, and preferre riches, pleaſures, faire houſes, conuenient dwellings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19236:8"/> Gods word, heauen, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, how careleſſe are they to preuent dangers. Happily there is many a <hi>Shemei</hi> wiſe enough to meet <hi>Dauid</hi> in time for his owne ſauegard, 1. Sam. 19. 19. many an vniuſt <hi>Steward</hi> wiſe enough to preuent beggery, Luke, 16. many a <hi>Pilate</hi> wiſe enough to keep in <hi>Ceſars</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, Ioh. 19. 13. many like thoſe of <hi>Tyrus</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> wiſe enough to make peace with thoſe which are too ſtrong for them, Act. 12. 20. and generally men are quick-witted to keep fire from their houſes, the theife from their gold, to auoid infectious places, ſtinking pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, poiſons, &amp;c. and yet in the meane time runne on in their ſinnes without all dread of danger, feare of iudgments, of Gods wrath, of hell it ſelfe: and ſuch as theſe may be accounted <hi>wiſe, caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, circumſpect, &amp;c.</hi> but alaſſe, it is but poore wiſedome for a man to be afraid of the frying panne, and not of the fire; for a man to feare ſickeneſſe, want, &amp;c. and not to be afraid of hell it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, how negligent are they to prouide for future time, all their whole
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19236:8"/> care beeing only for things preſent, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent pleaſures, delights, &amp;c. altogether neglecting that immortall, vndefiled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, reſerued for them in heauen. Infinite is their greedineſſe after gold and ſiluer, their thirſt more then a drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie-mans after drinke: all their ioy is to ſlap in the filthy puddles, and to rake in the ſtinking dunghills of this world to encreaſe their ſubſtance: and yet ſo farre from laying vp treaſures in heauen, that if a man ſhould but ſpeake to them of an heauenly conuerſation, and of laying vp in ſtore a <hi>good foundation for time to come,</hi> 1. Tim. 16. 19. it would be as wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as <hi>ſmoake</hi> to the eyes, or <hi>raine</hi> in harueſt. Pro. 26. 1. O brethren, who are fooles if theſe be wiſe? would wee not count him for a ſenſeleſſe perſon, that would ſpend much time in trimming his garments, &amp; ſuffer his body (which is farre better then raiment) to periſh thorough famine and hunger? but farre more ſenſeleſſe are thoſe men which pamper the body (which is but as it were a cloath or a garment to the ſoule) and ſuffer their deareſt darlings, their ſoules which are farre better then their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19236:9"/> bodies, nay far more worth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a world, nay then a 1000. worlds to periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. <hi>Vnderſtand yee vnwiſe amongst the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 64 8.</note> 
               <hi>people, and yee fooles when will you be wiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> And let this which hath been deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, teach vs to pray to the Lord, as <hi>Paul</hi> did for the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> that God would <hi>fill vs with the knowledge of his will,</hi> Col. 1. 17. Let it ſtirre vs vp to <hi>call</hi> for <hi>wiſedome,</hi> and to <hi>crie</hi> for <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> Pro. 1. Let it prouoke vs to labour after heauenly wiſedome: for if thou want this, though thou wert able to diſcourſe of the <hi>Pleyades,</hi> and <hi>Orion,</hi> Iob. 38. 39. of the Sunne, and Moone, and ſtarres; though thou wert able, with king <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> to diſcourſe of trees and plants, euen from the Cedar in Libanon, to the hyſſope that ſprings out of the wall; though thou wert able to diſcourſe of beaſts, and ſoules, and creeping things, and fiſhes, 1. King. 4. 33. though thou wert as learned as <hi>Moſes,</hi> Act. 7. 22. as politike in ſtate-affaires as <hi>Achitophel,</hi> 2. Sam. 16. 23. yet if thou beeſt not wiſe to ſaluation, thou art but a <hi>Naball,</hi> a ſtarke foole in Gods eſteem: according as it is written, <hi>The wiſedome of this world
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19236:9"/> is fooliſhneſſe with God,</hi> 1. Cor. 3. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, this doctrine may be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall to diſcouer the vanitie of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conceit amongſt vs, (<hi>viz.</hi>) That thoſe which can multiply proiects, goe beyond others in buying and bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or can diſappoint the practiſes of their enemies, that ſuch men are wiſe men: and as for thoſe that the Spirit calls and ſtyles by the name of <hi>wiſe,</hi> ſuch as watch at the gates of wiſedom, Prou. 8. 33. and call and crie for wiſdome and vnderſtanding, Prou. 1. ſuch are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally condemned of folly; inſomuch that the world wonders at them, and winke with their eye, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, Prou. 6. 13. and lade them with taunts and ſcoffes, as the ſillieſt people vnder heauen. And that which I haue deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, doth notably confute this vaine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion: for whomſoeuer they account wiſe, and the moſt wiſe, God accounts fooles, and the moſt fooles. And hence it is, that <hi>Salomon</hi> doth ſo be-foole the vnregenerate man: <hi>Fooles deſpiſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> Prou. 1. 7. <hi>You fooles, how long will you loue fooliſhneſſe?</hi> v. 22. <hi>Eaſe ſlayeth the foole,</hi> v. 32. <hi>I ſaw amongſt the fooles a man
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19236:10"/> deſtitute of vnderſtanding,</hi> Prou. 7. 7. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your wayes, O yee fooliſh,</hi> Prou. 9. 6. And ſo the rich man in the Goſpel, as wiſe as he was, is ſtyled by the name of a <hi>foole,</hi> Luk. 12. 20. Contrariwiſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they account fooles, them doth the Lord account for wiſe: <hi>He that keeps Gods commandements is wiſe,</hi> Deut. 4. 5. <hi>They which feare God, and depart from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, are wiſe: the feare of God is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of wiſedome, and to depart from euill is vnderſtanding,</hi> Pſal. 111. 16. Iob. 28. 28. <hi>Yea,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>who ſo ſeemeth wiſe in this world, let him be a foole that he may be wiſe,</hi> 1. Cor. 1. 20. And therfore though men abound with carnall policie, though their heads be as full of ſubtill fetches as this Church is full of aire, yet God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts them ſtarke fooles, I was about to ſay, wiſe fooles: witnes that of <hi>Paul, Hee catcheth the wiſe in their owne crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and he knowes that the thoughts of the wiſe are vaine,</hi> 1. Cor. 3. 20.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that Kings &amp; Iudges are called vpon for, is <hi>learning; Be learned</hi>
               <note place="margin">Learned.</note> 
               <hi>O ye Iudges, &amp;c.</hi> Some tranſlate it, be <hi>you inſtructed,</hi> others be you <hi>chaſtiſed,</hi> others bee you <hi>warned,</hi> ſome others bee you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19236:10"/> 
               <hi>reformed:</hi> for mine owne part, I entend to follow our iudicious tranſlators that haue turned it thus: <hi>Bee learned, O yee Iudges, &amp;c.</hi> and indeed learning implieth all theſe, both <hi>inſtruction,</hi> and <hi>reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> both <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the firſt ſenſe <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſaid to be <hi>learned,</hi> Act. 7. 22. and, Neh. 8. 13. the <hi>Elders</hi> of Iſrael are ſaid to haue been <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed,</hi> or to haue <hi>learned</hi> Gods law.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, learning implyeth <hi>reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>practiſe: Learne of mee</hi> (ſaith Chriſt,) and what ſhould they learne of him, but <hi>meekeneſſe</hi> and <hi>humility? I am meeke and lowly,</hi> Matth. 11. 29. and, Eph. 4. 7. <hi>Walke not henceforth as other Gentiles haue done, in vanitie of their minds, hauing their cogitations darkened: but you haue not ſo learned Chriſt:</hi> and, Iſa. 1. 16. <hi>Waſh you, make you cleane, and ceaſe to do euill, learne to doe well, &amp;c.</hi> So as here I haue occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to exhort to a twofold duty. Firſt, to labour after knowledge. Secondly, to practiſe according to knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>2</label> Firſt, we muſt learne what the will &amp; pleaſure of God is. In Act. 9. 37. <hi>Dorcas</hi> is called a <hi>diſciple:</hi> and, Ioh. 13. 38. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> is called a <hi>diſciple: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19236:11"/> is tearmed a <hi>diſciple,</hi> Ioh. 19. 10. All the Chriſtians in <hi>Antiochia</hi> are tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>diſciples,</hi> Act. 11. 26. and wherefore, I pray you, are they ſo ſtyled? but to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate vnto vs their deſire to learne in Chriſts ſchoole: for theſe two, to bee a ſcholler in Chriſts ſchoole, and a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple are both one: and this I dare ſay with a graue Diuine, that he which is no<note place="margin">H. pag. 83.</note> diſciple, is no Chriſtian; and would to God there were more diſciples amongſt vs. How iuſtly may the Lord complain of vs, as he did of the Iewiſh nation; <hi>The oxe knowes his owner, and the aſſe his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters cribbe, but Iſrael hath not knowne me,</hi> Iſa. 1. 3. <hi>The Storke of the aire knowes his appointed time, and the turtle, and crane, and ſwallow, obſerue the time of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, but my people knowes not the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord,</hi> Ier. 8. 7. Infinite is our blindneſſe and blockiſhneſſe in matters of God, and which is moſt lamentable of all, there are fewe diſciples amongſt vs; yea may not wiſdome crie out in our ſtreets, <hi>O you fooles, how long will you loue fooliſhneſſe, and hate knowledge?</hi> Pro. 1. 20. And if this ſeeme too generall, conſider we what reaſons may mooue vs, to cal &amp;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19236:11"/> crie for knowledge and vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>And amongſt many, I will content my ſelfe with theſe two.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, we muſt learne as much as wee can poſſibly of Gods will, leaſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance carry vs headlong into a world of ſinne; <hi>This people doe erre in their hearts, becauſe they haue not known my waies,</hi> Pſal. 95. 10. yea, and ſometimes all manner of ſinne is ſtyled by the name of <hi>ignorance,</hi> becauſe that the ignorant man runnes into all ſinne: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. the High Prieſt once a yeare of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a ſacrifice for himſelfe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for himſelfe, and for the ignorances of the people,</hi> Heb. 9. 7. the Apoſtle calls all their ſinnes by the name of <hi>ignorance:</hi> for that ignorance is as it were the root, and ſpawne, and mother of all ſinne, and vſhers in a world of ſin; <hi>Spirituall pride,</hi> Rom. 10. 3. <hi>Idolatry,</hi> Gal. 4. 8. <hi>blaſphemy, oppreſſion,</hi> 1. Tim. 1. 13. and indeed what not? for whither runs he that is blind? ſo as here is one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſtirre vs vp to learne and to bee good diſciples in Chriſts ſchool-houſe, ſince ignorance is the prime cauſe of all vngodlineſſe.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19236:12"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, want of knowledge draws downe iudgement, both temporary, and eternall.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it cauſes <hi>temporary</hi> iudgements, as baniſhment; <hi>Becauſe they haue no knowledge, therefore they are gone into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie,</hi> Iſa. 5. 13. Yea, ignorance cauſeth God to deſtroy the moſt famous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned places of the world. Let <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> witneſſe for me; <hi>The defenced Citie</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>ſhall be deſolate, and left like a wilderneſſe:</hi> and marke the reaſon, <hi>for it is a people of no vnderſtanding: therefore he that made them ſhall haue no compaſſion of them,</hi> Iſa. 27. 10. 11. and, Hoſ. 4. 6. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt refuſed knowledge, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe thee: and becauſe thou haſt forgotten the law of thy God, I wil alſo forget thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> And againe in the ſame chapter; <hi>The Lord hath a controuerſie with the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the land, becauſe there is no truth, nor mercie, nor knowledge of God in the land, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ignorance cauſeth eternall iudgement. <hi>As many as ſinne without the Law, ſhall periſh without the Law,</hi> Rom. 2. 12. <hi>Hee which knowes not his maſters will and doth it not ſhall be beaten,</hi> Luk. 12.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19236:12"/> 47. and 2. Theſſ. 1. 8. <hi>The Sonne of man ſhall come in ſlaming fire, rendring venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to thoſe which know him not. And if our Goſpell be hidde, it is hid to them which are loſt, whoſe eyes the deuill hath blinded that the light of the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt ſhould not ſhine vnto them.</hi> 2. Cor. 4. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> And therefore ſince wee muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to be learned in Gods lawes, ſince ignorance is the mother of errour, the cauſe of iudgements; ſince we ought to be <hi>fulfilled with knowledge,</hi> Col. 3. 16. and the word muſt dwell plentiouſly in vs, and we muſt <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> Ioh. 5. 39. here then are our Romaniſts confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that haue painted ouer the face of ignorance, and ſtyle her the <hi>mother of deuotion:</hi> and vnder this pretence haue (as one ſaith) ſet locke and key vpon the Scriptures, forbidding the common people the ſearching of the Scriptures: abuſing that diuine precept of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour, <hi>caſt not holy things to dogges,</hi> Matth. 7. 6. as if all Gods people were dogges and ſwine: but what ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. Theſſ. 5. 27. <hi>I charge you in the Lord, that this Epiſtle be read to all the brethren
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19236:13"/> the Saints.</hi> And againe, Rom. 1. 3. the Apoſtle writes his Epiſtle generally <hi>to al the Saints at Rome.</hi> And wherefore then doe the Papiſts barre the people from the vſe of <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle would haue common; and not from the vſe of <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles alone, but from the whole vſe of Scripture?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, ſince God calls vpon vs to be <hi>learned</hi> in his word, this reprooues the blockiſh ignorance in theſe times: for now are the daies come that we may crie out with <hi>Dauid, there is none that vnderſtands,</hi> Pſal. 14. 1. We liue vnder a glorious ſunſhine, <hi>but this is condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that light is come into the world, and men loue darkeneſſe more then light,</hi> Ioh. 3. 19. God hath been maruailouſly rich in mercy, in vouchſafing vnto vs means of knowledge. The meſſengers of God crie vnto vs, ſaying, <hi>this is the way, walke in it,</hi> Iſa. 30. 21. the golden bels of <hi>Aaron</hi> rings in euery place; &amp; indeed we want neither bookes, for God hath <hi>written vnto vs the great things of his lawe,</hi> Oſe. 8. nor tutors, to open vnto vs <hi>Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,</hi> Act. 20. 20. nor nothing ſit for Chriſts ſchollers to encreaſe our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19236:13"/> and yet notwithſtanding our tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, teaching, preaching, planting, ſowing, watering, yet how many are there that knowe not wherefore they were ſent into the world. Queſtion a drunkard about wine and ſtrong drink, a couetous man about building and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down, of digging, ditching, plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſowing, and therein you ſhall finde them very ſenſible and intelligible, quicke either to conceiue or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; but talke to them concerning thoſe admirable myſteries of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, iuſtification, &amp;c. and they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no more then if a man ſhould read them a peece of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> or <hi>Plato,</hi> or any other author in a ſtrange tongue. O that ſuch treuants as theſe would thinke vpon that ſaying, Ioh. 14. 22. <hi>If I had not come and ſpoken to them, they had had no ſinne: but now they haue no cloak for their ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, ſince God calleth vpon vs to be <hi>learned</hi> in Gods lawes, hence it followes further that we muſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues with a little meaſure and <hi>modicum</hi> of knowledge, but wee muſt ſtriue to be <hi>learned;</hi> that is, to be full of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19236:14"/> knowledge. For he is not a learned man that knowes two or three grammar rules, but he that is skild in the tongues, in the arts, and ſciences: ſo he is not a learned Chriſtian, that vnderſtands two or three eaſie principles; but hee that hath the ſpirit of wiſedome, and reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, through the knowledge of Chriſt, that haue their vnderſtanding lightned, and <hi>know what is the hope of their calling,</hi> Epheſ. 1. 17. Well then, ſince the Spirit calls vpon vs to be <hi>learned,</hi> therefore ſay I, that as good ſtudents are inſatiably thirſty after learning, like <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> that was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, indeffatigable in paines, and vnweariable in his labours for the encreaſe of his knowledge: ſuch alſo is the eager affection of all ſuch as are Chriſts Diſciples, and right learned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that their thirſt after knowledge cannot be quenched.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But ſome man may happily replie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee, that euery man cannot be ſo great a ſcholler as you ſpeake of: God hath not giuen his gifts alike vnto all men.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> And to this I anſwer againe, that though God giues 10. talents to one,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19236:14"/> and but 5. to another, yet would there not be a dunce in a countrey, if men would but obſerue theſe rules follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to pray for knowledge; <hi>If any</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Prayer.</note> 
               <hi>man want wiſedome, let him aske it of God,</hi> Iam. 1. 5. The way to haue the eyes of our vnderſtanding opened, is to pray to God with blinde <hi>Bartimeus, O ſonne of Dauid, haue mercy on vs, Lord, that we may receiue our ſight,</hi> Mat. 10. 51. <hi>Luther,</hi> that was ſo mighty in the Scriptures, was wont to proteſt that he had more reuealed to him by praier, then by ſtudy and reading. But though this be a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table meanes of illumination, yet at this time I intend to follow the phraſe of my text. And this is all I ſay, that if a ſtudent will be a good proficient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; Firſt, he muſt plie his priuate ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: Secondly, he muſt frequent learned exerciſes: Thirdly, he muſt be much in conference: Fourthly, he muſt be much in contemplation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he muſt ſtudie hard: Learning<note place="margin">2 Reading.</note> is not gotten without ſtudie. <hi>Socrates</hi> would read and meditate 20. houres to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and <hi>Cato</hi> got not his learning
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19236:15"/> with beeing idle, <hi>Heluo erat librorum, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros legebat nec eorum lectione ſatiari po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit.</hi> Whoſoeuer will be a good profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in Chriſts ſchoole, muſt take the Apoſtles aduice to ſearch the Scripturs, yea and ſpend time in reading of godly bookes: but I name the Scriptures eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, becauſe all the reſt of the ſheafes muſt doe reuerence to this ſheafe: <hi>Let not the word of this law depart from thee,</hi> ſaith God, Ioſ. 1. 8. And what ſaith he to the King, Deut. 17. 19. <hi>He ſhall reade the words of this Lawe all the dayes of his life, that hee may learne to feare the Lord his God, and to keepe the words of this Law, &amp;c.</hi> And here, brethren, is the reaſon why there are ſo many vnlearned ones a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, euen becauſe the Lord hath written vnto vs the great things of his <hi>Law, and wee doe not regard them,</hi> Hoſ. 8. 13. here is the reaſon, becauſe we are like to many idle ſchollers that haue their ſtudies full of good bookes, which lie moulding vpon their ſhelues, and are couered ouer with duſt, whilſt they lauiſh away their time at cheſſe, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, or worſe recreations, &amp; no maruel then if they increaſe not in knowledge
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19236:15"/> and learning: and thus it is with many in the ſchoole of Chriſt; come into their houſes, and you ſhall ſee their ſhelues adorned with good bookes, the bible and other godly treatiſes; but alaſſe they hunt after riches, and friends, &amp;c. and are ſuch ſtrangers to Gods word, that they read not a chapter in a whole moneth together, and no meruaile then if they be vnlearned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to increaſe knowledge,<note place="margin">3 Hearing.</note> we muſt frequent the aſſemblies of the Saints. The houſe of God is the Lords ſchoolehouſe, the miniſters of the word are the Lords teachers, Eph. 4. 11. 1. Tim. 2. 7. The preaching of the word may be compared to the reading of a Lecture: and how I pray you can a man hope to gaine learning, that hates his tutor, ſhames all godly exerciſes, and will not once ſet his foote within the ſchoole doores. O that I had not iuſt cauſe to crie out with the Prophet, <hi>Oh earth, earth, earth, heare the word of the Lord,</hi> Ier. 22. 19. when men would not heare, hee calls vpon the dead earth to hearken. And ſince the times are nowe come vpon vs, that wiſedome cryeth in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19236:16"/> the high places, <hi>and is deſpiſed amongst vs,</hi> Prou. 1. 21. ſince God hath raiſed vp ſo many faithfull teachers and tutors al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to euerie ſchoole a teacher; ſince we haue Lecture vpon Lecture, Sermon vpon Sermon, and ſo few reſort to the ſchool-houſe; ſince the word is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the very burthen of the Lord, <hi>Heare, O heauens, and I will ſpeake, and let the earth heare the words of my mouth,</hi> Deut. 32. 1. O heauens, beare ye witnes of the horrible vnthankefulneſſe of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp; let the dead earth teſtifie of their contempt of Gods word, or if there be any that haue eares to heare, let them heare, Reu. 3. 22. If there be any that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to come out of their blindneſſe and ignorance, let them thirſt after the word, as the dry ground after the ſweet dewes and ſhowers of raine: let them deſire the <hi>ſincere milke of the word,</hi> 1. Pet. 2. 2. and hearken to the voice of Chriſt ſpeaking to vs by his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> 2. Cor. 5. 28. To ſpeake plainely, let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort diligently to the ſchool-houſe, and ſo ſhall they be enlightened, and learne what is the good will and pleaſure of God.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:19236:16"/>
            <p>A third meanes to encreaſe in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">4 Conference.</note> is conference with thoſe which are learned: the way to be learned, is to learne of euery man, <hi>Sapientior omnibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ris, ſi ab omnibus diſcere volueris, qui ab omnibus accipiunt omnibus ditiores ſunt,</hi> ſaith one: thou ſhalt be wiſer then any man, if thou wouldeſt learne of euery man. The Ethyopian gained more by conference with <hi>Philip,</hi> then he gained with much reading, Act. 8. 39. And I remember what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Rom. 1. 12. <hi>I long to ſee you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that I might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſome ſpirituall gift amongſt you, and that I might be comforted together with you, through our mutuall faith, both yours and mine.</hi> The Apoſtle was a man full of knowledge, and the poore Saints in Rome were many thouſand degrees in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to him, and yet for the futher encreaſe of his knowledge, and for his further confirmation &amp; eſtabliſhment, he deſires to take a iourney to them, and doubts not but to gaine ſomewhat by conuerſing with the moſt ſimplieſt Chriſtian. And the truth is, that a man ſhall ſometimes learne from the weakeſt, that which he could neuer
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19236:17"/> learne by conuerſing with the moſt wiſe and literate;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quod tu non noſti fortaſſis nouit aſſellus.</hi> And here is another eſpeciall cauſe of our intollerable ignorance, becauſe there is ſo much ſtrangeneſſe amongſt vs, and one Chriſtian will not conuerſe with another, and conferre of good things; but either they ſhunne all ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, or if they meet, all the time is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and deuoured in gibing and iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, idle talke, frothy ſpeeches, if not in ſwearing, blaſphemie, &amp;c. Here is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother cauſe of ignorance, the remedy is godly conference.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the laſt meanes to attaine<note place="margin">5 Meditation.</note> to learning, is contemplation. Though a ſtudent read much, reſort to lectures, conferre, yet all will profit him little without meditation. I know that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, hearing, &amp;c. are notable meanes to encreaſe knowledg, and yet all theſe will auaile little without meditation. The word may aptly be compared to meate, meditation to diſgeſtion: what good doth meat if a man ſhall vomit it vp againe as ſoone as euer he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued it into his ſtomacke, and what
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19236:17"/> will it profit a man to heare, conferre, &amp;c. if we ſhall as it were inſtantly vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit vp all againe? meditation is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life of our deuotion. And for this cauſe after <hi>Paul</hi> had exhorted <hi>Timothie</hi> to ſundry duties, hee addes this alſo, <hi>hac meditare,</hi> 1. Tim. 4. 15. <hi>Oh, how I loue thy law, it is my continuall meditation,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 110. 97. I will not ſtand to ſpeake of <hi>Iſaacks</hi> contemplation, Gen. 24. 64. nor <hi>Ezekiahs,</hi> Iſa. 38. 14. nor of the virgin <hi>Maries,</hi> Luk. 2. 10. I will, to quicken you vp to meditation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with that place, Ier. 82. 11. <hi>The whole land is fallen to deſolation, becauſe there is none that conſiders.</hi> And thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing deliuered rules for the encreaſe of <hi>knowledge,</hi> I come yet to a fourth vſe. (<hi>viz.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, to pitty the ignorance of others, and to labour to draw them out of their ignorance. And here ſpare me a little, till I haue directed my ſpeech to three ſorts of men.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to Patrons: If Magiſtrates in<note place="margin">Patrons.</note> corporation-townes, where free ſchooles are erected, ſhall chooſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull and negligent Teachers, muſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19236:18"/> not the ſchollers bee vnlearned, when their maſters are vnlearned? If one blind man leade another, <hi>they fall both into the ditch,</hi> Matth. 15. 14. I muſt not feare the faces of men, and I will be bold to tell many gentlemen that they are cauſes of the ouer-ſpreading ſinne of ignorance, and that their couetouſneſſe is the cauſe why whole pariſhes generally are ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant. For why? many gentlemen are growne to that paſſe, that they will doe any thing for lucre: I doe not accuſe all, nay, I can acquit many out of mine own knowledge: but there are a great many alſo that caſt lots vpon Chriſts coate, ſuch as ſell the portion of the Lord for mony: and prouided that they may fill their bags with gold and ſiluer, would preſent they care not whome to their benefice. I could willingly ſpend ſome more time in reproofe of ſuch a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe generation, that care not whoſe ſoule fries in hell, ſo they may haue two or three yeares profit before hand, or a yeerely reſeruation to themſelues of the tithes and tenths. But I ſhall haue occaſion to returne againe to this point.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19236:18"/>
            <p>Secondly, a word or two, to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters:<note place="margin">2 Miniſters.</note> for as I ſaid, if Tutors be naught, the pupills muſt needs be naught. The miniſters of the word are the <hi>ſalt of the earth,</hi> Matth. 5. 13. the light of Chriſts myſticall body: and therefore if they be vnlearned, or careleſſe, needs muſt they bring blindneſſe to the whole body. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſe, that we haue cauſe to complaine with the Prophet, <hi>Their watchmen are blinde, they haue no knowledge, they are dumbe dogges and cannot barke, they ſleepe and delight in ſleeping,</hi> Eſa. 56. 10. God forbid that I ſhould caſt ſtones at the head of innocencie. I know that there are many faithfull labourers, ſuch as <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the word aright,</hi> 2. Tim. 2. 15. ſuch as labour in the <hi>word and doctrine,</hi> 1. Tim. 2. 15. ſuch as may ſay of themſelues, as <hi>Paul</hi> of himſelfe, <hi>In wearineſſe often, in watchings often,</hi> 2. Cor. 11. 27. and yet beſides theſe, there are ſome amongſt vs, <hi>idoll-ſhepheards, ſlowbellies, dumb dogs, loyterers,</hi> nay murtherers, that open not a pulpet dore once in an whole yeare, except vpon ſome high and feſtiual day: and what are theſe but murtherers? and conſcious of murther in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19236:19"/> for what cruelty is like to ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruelty? and if <hi>Abells</hi> blood, nay euery drop of <hi>Abells</hi> blood, (as the originall will beare it, thy <hi>brothers bloods</hi> cryeth<note place="margin">Gen. 5. 10.</note> vnto me from the ground, yea euery <hi>droppe</hi> of thy brothers blood:) if I ſay e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery droppe of <hi>Abells</hi> blood cryed for vengeance againſt <hi>Cain,</hi> what a fearefull crie ſhal the blood of many ſoules make before the throane of God, asking ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance againſt their paſtors, which haue ſtarued their ſoules to death, by detay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and holding from them the bread of life?</p>
            <p>3. Laſtly, to conclude with Parents<note place="margin">Maſters of families.</note> and maſters of priuate families, whoſe negligence in teaching and inſtructing their children and ſeruants, is an other cauſe of our ouer-ſpreading ignorance: for the Preachers of the word may la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and <hi>be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon,</hi> 1. Tim. 4. 1. and all to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if maſters of families neglect their duties: neither doe I wonder to ſee ſo many men and women ſo intollerably, and incredibly ignorant, ſince to ſpeake truth, a man had as good be ſome mans beaſt, as either their ſonne or ſeruant.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19236:19"/> For what doe their maſters or parents regard them, more then their bruite beaſts? they feed their ſeruants, and ſo they doe their cattell; they worke their ſeruants, and ſo they doe their beaſts: if any of their ſeruants be ſicke and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, they will ſeeke out for remedie, and ſo they will for their beaſts. Againe, their care to inſtruct and teach their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and bruit beaſts, is much one: they teach their children and ſeruants, nothing but how to plow, ſowe, ditch, &amp;c. and as much as this they teach their cattell, their oxen to drawe, their horſes to pace, &amp;c. and therefore no wonder though their children and ſeruants be as ignorant as <hi>the horſe and mule, that haue none vnderſtanding.</hi> O that maſters of families would learne, to ſpend ſome of that precious time which they miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpend in twatling and idle talking, in backbiting, ſlandering, &amp;c. in teaching and inſtructing their families, whoſe blood ſhall otherwiſe bee required at their hands if they periſh!</p>
            <p>The next concluſion gathered out of this ſecond exhortation was this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>3</label> That wee muſt adde practiſe to our
<pb facs="tcp:19236:20"/> knowledge: <hi>Not the hearers of the lawe are righteous before God, but the doers of the law ſhalbe iuſtified,</hi> Rom. 2. 13.</q>
            <p>For the further proofe of this point, you may at your leaſure reade theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Ioh. 15. 14. Ioh. 10. 27. Matth. 7. 24. Luk. 8. 20. Matt. 12. 50. and if theſe may not ſuffice thee, then I ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that all knowledge without practiſe is vneffectuall, and of no force to free from condemnation. <hi>Though I knewe all knowledge,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, yet were I nothing if I wanted loue,</hi> 1. Cor. 13. yea if a bare &amp; naked knowledge would ſaue, then the deuills themſelues ſhould be ſaued; for they know enough: <hi>Ieſus I know, and Paul I knowe,</hi> ſaid the euill <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> Act. 19. 15. And if you reade Matth. 4. 6. there you ſhall ſee, that the diuel is a cunning Scripturian; <hi>It is written,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that he will giue his angels charge ouer thee, &amp;c.</hi> v. 6. Suppoſe then that thou haſt neuer ſo much knowledge, ſuppoſe thou haſt read as much as <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that he turned ouer all the whole librarie of the Greeks; yet if thou know much and practiſe iuſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19236:20"/> why ſhould not the deuils (which know more) be ſaued as well as thou.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, all knowledge without practiſe is not onely vaine, but perilous: <hi>He that knowes his Maſters will, and doth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 27.</note> 
               <hi>it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes:</hi> and Iam. 4. 17. <hi>He that knoweth how to do well, and doth it not, to him it is ſinne:</hi> and as one ſaith well vpon theſe words, <hi>not ſinne ſimply, but ſinne with a witnes, or ſinne with aduantage. If I had not come and ſpoken to them, they had had no ſinne, but nowe they haue no cloake for their ſinnes,</hi> Ioh. 15. 22. And how doth our Sauiour Chriſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid thoſe cities where they had ſo much meanes; and doubtleſſe a great deale of knowledge? <hi>Woe to thee Cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin, wee to thee Bethſaida: for if the great works that were done in you, had beene done in Tyrus and Sidon, they had repented long agoe in ſackecloath and aſhes,</hi> Matth. 11. 20. By Gods word (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>)<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> man ſinneth ſo much the more, how much the more by the word he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that to be ſinne which he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> All which being granted, let vs learn to take S. <hi>Peters</hi> counſell, <hi>to adde to our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19236:21"/> knowledge temperance, to our temperance patience, and to our patience godlineſſe,</hi> 2. Pet. 1. 5. for otherwiſe, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> wrote to the people of <hi>Antioch,</hi> that were deſirous to gaine knowledge, and yet were ready to ſweare, and vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery occaſion to rappe out oaths; <hi>The more</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that you know, and the oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you heare, &amp;c. the more you ſinne againſt God, and the more you encreaſe your puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe you liue in the practiſe of thoſe courſes which you know to be ſinnefull.</hi> And would to God that our hollow-hearted profeſſors, which know Gods will, yea and carie before them the lampe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and yet lead their liues after ſuch a manner, that if the deuil himſelfe were in a bodily ſhape, he could liue no wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; vſurers, extortioners, cheaters, ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, &amp;c. would to God, I ſay, they would conſider it, that their knowledge and gifts ſhall but helpe them on the more roundly to hell fire, without obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. I ſpeake not againſt profeſſion, neither againſt knowledge; I knowe there can be no ſaluation without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor no obedience without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; but this I ſay moreouer, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19236:21"/> is the end of our knowledge. And if we know the Law, and yet ſinne againſt it, then ſhall that be verefied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, Rom. 2. 12. <hi>As many as ſinne in the Lawe, ſhall be iudged by the Lawe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I come to the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances<note place="margin">Firſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the time.</note> expreſſed in this text. And firſt of the time, <hi>Bee wiſe now, O yee Kings; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>augnattah,</hi> euen preſently, while the Lords ſcepter is in his hand readie to ſmite, and before he ſmites you: euen out of hand furniſh your ſelues with true wiſedome and learning, leaſt you bee broken and bruiſed in peices. And here note two things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that repentance muſt not bee deferred.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the conſideration of Gods iudgements, ought to mooue vs repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>4</label> Firſt, that repentance muſt not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid, I will referre you to thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Iſa. 55. 6. Heb. 3. 7. Luk. 1. 57. Act. 17. 30. 2. Cor. 6. 2. and onely inſiſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on two or three reaſons of this point, leaſt time preuent me.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then it ſtands vs in hand to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, becauſe of the vncertainty of our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19236:22"/> life: <hi>nihil certius morte, hora mortis nihil</hi>
               <note place="margin">Life vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</note> 
               <hi>incertius,</hi> nothing more certaine then death, then the time when we ſhall die, or the place where, or the manner how, nothing is more vncertaine. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ioh</hi> compares the life of man to a <hi>candle,</hi> Iob. 15. 17. for as a candle though it burnes neuer ſo clearely, yet a little wet, or a ſmall gale of winde will blow it out ſuddenly; ſo though a man be neuer ſo luſty and ſtrong; yet a little greife or ſickneſſe may be to him, as the winde is to the candle, or rather as the hammer is to the potters pot, breaking theſe earthly veſſells of ours in peeces. Goe to then, thou which ſayeſt to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row will be time enough to repent, I am yet in the flowre &amp; prime of my youth, youth muſt ſowe the wilde oates, &amp;c. take heed that thou beeſt not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away like <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> in thy dead ſleep, 2. Sam. 4. 7. or topt off ſuddenly like an eare of <hi>corne,</hi> Iob 24. 24. like the churle in the Goſpel, Luk. 12. 6. or <hi>Herod,</hi> Act. 12. 13. or <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphyra,</hi> Act. 5. 5. The men of <hi>Sodome</hi> dreamed not of a ſtorme of fire in the morning, nor the men of the old world for a flood of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19236:22"/> but <hi>Lot</hi> was no ſooner vpon mount <hi>Zoar,</hi> nor <hi>Noah</hi> within his Arke, but that the Lord rained fire from heauen vpon the one, and opened the windows of heauen, and deſtroyed the other with waters, Geneſ. 7. 20. Gen. 19. 23. And therefore thou which ſaieſt, I will ſtay a while longer, and I will repent in my man-age or dotage; take heed that thou beeſt not vpon thy ſick bed, in thy win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſheet before that time comes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, wee muſt turne from our ſinns without delay, becauſe all our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice is onely due to God: <hi>Remember thy Creator in the daies of thy youth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> Eccl. 12. 1. the wiſeman would haue vs remember God betimes; and why? becauſe he is our Creator: it is he which made vs, and therefore we are his by right of creation, and owe all our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to him alone. And, Eccl. 31. <hi>There is an appointed time for all things vnder the Sunne, a time to plant, a time to build, &amp;c.</hi> but he ſaith not, there is a time to curſe, and a time to banne, a time to whoore, and a time to ſteale; becauſe that God hath allotted out no time to ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, deferring is dangerous; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:19236:23"/> repentance is Gods gift, and not in our owne power; yea, and the longer we deferre, the harder will it be to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: the longer we ſuffer our houſes to runne into delapidations, the greater will our trouble and charges be to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire them:</p>
            <q>Si non vic hodie, cras minus aptus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</q>
            <p>I remember what I read concerning our Sauiours raiſing vp of <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of the graue. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, that he <hi>groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſpirit, and was troubled in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> Ioh. 11. 33. and what was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that our Sauiour groaned more now then at other times; a great diuine giues<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> this reaſon, <hi>becauſe Lazarus had beene dead foure dayes:</hi> and ſo I ſay, when men are not onely dead in ſin, but haue been dead many dayes, and haue laine rotting and ſoaking in their ſinnes, and that not foure dayes, but foure yeares, nay four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares, inſomuch that their bones are filled with the <hi>ſinnes of their youth,</hi> Iob. 20. 10. is it not a great miracle if theſe ſhould be quickned &amp; raiſed vp againe? Oh take we heede that ſinne plead not cuſtome, that we ſuffer not our wounds
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19236:23"/> to putrifie; I meane, let not our ſinnes grow incurable through our negligence. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>But to day while it is called to day, let vs ſeeke the Lord,</hi> Heb. 3. 13. <hi>while wee haue time,</hi> Gal. 4. 13. <hi>while wee haue light,</hi> Ioh. 12. 35. whlie we haue day before vs, let vs turne vnto God. And as we read of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he went to ſacrifice his ſonne <hi>Iſaack</hi> early in the morning, Gen. 22. 3. ſo I ſay of our ſinnes, that we loue as dearely as euer <hi>Abraham</hi> loued his ſonne <hi>Iſaac,</hi> or <hi>Dauid</hi> his <hi>Abſolom,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with them, crucifie them, ſacrifice them; yea and goe about to offer vp thy ſacrifice betimes: <hi>offer vp your ſelues a liuing ſacrifice,</hi> Rom. 12. 1. <hi>In the morning ſow thy ſeed, and in the euening withdraw not thine hand,</hi> Pro. 27. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, this doctrine reprooues thoſe which deferre their repentance, to their middle age, olde age, dotage, death bed, &amp; then when their breath ſits vpon the tips of their tongues, readie to flit and flie away (as if they had repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in a ſtring) then they will repent for all; and in the interim, the Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them away ſuddenly, before their prefixed time is come, and their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19236:24"/> ſoules lie frying in hel before they were aware. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>now is the acceptable time,</hi> now is the day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, now is the time while the gates of mercy ſtand wide open: and therfore now, euen now let vs be wiſe, and fil our lamps full of oyle, leaſt that hereafter we knocke with the fiue fooliſh virgins, and cry, <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> and it prooue too late, Matth. 22. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>5</label> The next collection which I gathered was this, That the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods iudgements hanging ouer vs, ought to mooue vs to repentance. For the proofe of it, ſee 1. King. 21. 27. Luk. 15. 16. Ier. 18. 8. 2. Chron. 7. 14. I will vſe none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon to confirme it but this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that repentance is the beſt courſe to turne away Gods iudgements from vs; witnes the example of the <hi>Niniuites,</hi> Ion. 3. 9. The Prophet of the Lord prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched deſtruction againſt them, <hi>After fortie daies, and Nineueh ſhall bee deſtroyed, &amp;c.</hi> Well, and what courſe tooke the citizens for their owne ſafegard: <hi>Cry we mightily vnto God</hi> (ſaid the King to his ſubiects) <hi>turne wee from our euill wayes: who can tell whether the Lord will turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19236:24"/> from his fierce wrath, that we periſh not.</hi> And then it followes in the next verſe, <hi>that God repented him of the euill, &amp;c.</hi> And no leſſe remarkeable is that notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the good King <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> 2. Chro. 34. 27. <hi>Becauſe thine heart did melt, and thou didſt humble thy ſelfe before mee, and didſt weep, &amp;c. thou ſhalt not ſee all the euill, that I will bring vpon this place, and vpon his inhabitants.</hi> I will not trouble you, nor my ſelfe, with other proofes for the ratifying of this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, let it ſerue to condemne ſuch as adde ſinne to ſin, yea and euen then when the rodde of God is vpon their backes, while the Lord ſmites and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts them, euen then when they breake out into all manner of vngodlines, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, banning, murmuring, and by this meanes kindle the flame, and adde few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell to the fire. I know not whereto to compare them better, then to a man that ſhould ſee his houſe on fire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhould throw on buckets full of oyle to quench it; or ſhould caſt on faggots of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare wood, faggot after faggot, and ſo on ſtead of quenching kindle the fire: &amp; thus doe many, they thinke to quench
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19236:25"/> the fire with oyle: ſin is very fewell for Gods wrath, and when the wrath of God is kindled againſt them, the more God puniſhes, the more violently doe they laſh out into ſinne, ſweare worſe, rayle and murmure worſe then they did before: and what is this but to quench fire with oyle? and the courſe were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to quench the fire with teares of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe and repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, this leſſon is needfull for vs in theſe times, which may hourely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſome fearefull iudgement vpon vs: yea I feare, I feare, that the <hi>iudge ſtands at the doore,</hi> Iam. 5. 9. and is now ready to come vpon vs with a beſome of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation in his hand, to purge theſe <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gean</hi> ſtables of our tipling houſes, dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, filthy houſes: and if any man ſhall laugh in his ſleeue, and <hi>bleſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> Deut. 29. 19. and ſay, <hi>Tuſh, Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will doe neither good, nor euill;</hi> I anſwer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that the <hi>whole head</hi> is ſicke, and the <hi>whole heart heauie,</hi> Iſa. 1. 5. our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Gods word more then paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, all the damnable ſinnes of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Samaria</hi> ſwarme amongſt vs; our i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſſe, wantonneſſe, and millions of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19236:25"/> other ſinnes crie and roare to God for vengeance againſt vs: and haue we not cauſe to feare, leaſt God hath a <hi>contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie with the inhabitants of the Land;</hi> Hoſ. 4. 1. O brethren, that I could draw waters out of the hard rockes, ſome teares of repentance from the eyes of drunkards, whore-hunters, to quench the fire of Gods diſpleaſure kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. In the feare of God let vs humble our ſelues before God; let our hearts melt, our eyes ſpout out teares as a conduit ſpouts out water, let vs faſt and pray, and call and crie to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the decree come foorth, and we be made like <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Zeboim,</hi> like <hi>Gath</hi> of the Philiſtims, or like <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> or other famous cities and kingdomes, whoſe ſinnes hath laid them leuell with the earth. And this of the firſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, of the time.</p>
            <p>The ſecond followes of the perſons,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the perſons.</note> 
               <hi>Kings</hi> firſt, ſecondly <hi>Iudges:</hi> that is, thoſe rulers that exerciſe authority vnder Kings and Princes. And here I might ſtand vpon many particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>6</label> Firſt, that God plauges not, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he plagues, he giues warning; ſo he
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19236:26"/> doth in this place to the <hi>Kings</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudges:</hi> ſo he did giue warning to the men of the old world, before the flood came: thus he foretold of the <hi>Babylonian</hi> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity, of the deſtruction of Ieruſalem, &amp;c. though his bowe be euer bent, yet he neuer ſhoots one ſhaft but he giues warning, by his word, his miniſters, by ſignes and prodiges, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>7</label> Secondly, where he names <hi>Iudges</hi> as well as <hi>Kings,</hi> inferiour Magiſtrates as well as ſuperiours, that here againe we may obſerue, that Iudges muſt labour to get wiſedome as well as Kings and Princes: my meaning is, that thoſe that are in inferiour places muſt labour for wiſedome as well as thoſe that are in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour places: how can Kings rule wel, when their Magiſtrates be euill, how can Magiſtrates reforme the people, when the people are incorrigible, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>8</label> But I muſt make haſt: note againe, that though the common people had ſinned as well as the Kings and Iudges, yet the Spirit of God names onely theſe two, <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> becauſe they are for the moſt part led by the mighty:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Regis ad exemplu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> totus componitur orbis.</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:19236:26"/> If <hi>Herod</hi> deſpiſe Chriſt, his men of war will deſpiſe him alſo, Luk. 23. 11. If the king honour <hi>Mordecay, Haman</hi> his mortall enemy will honour him, Heſt. 6. 10. If the Scribes and Phariſes crie out againſt Chriſt, <hi>let him bee crucified,</hi> the common people will ſay the ſame tune, <hi>let him be crucified,</hi> Luk. 23. 23. If <hi>Ieroboam</hi> be an idolater, ſo will all the 10. Tribes, 1. King. 12. 28. If <hi>Conſtantine</hi> be a Chriſtian, hee makes a Chriſtian world. And thus the examples of great men like floods and inundations, doe carrie the common people headlong.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> And let this that hath beene ſpoken, ſerue for an <hi>item</hi> to all ſuch as are any wayes eminent, that they doe not for their liues giue an euill example, leaſt they ſinne like <hi>Ieroboam</hi> that ſinned, and made <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſinne: an euill example in great men, is like an ecclips of the ſun: much obſerued, and vſually the forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſome dearth or famine to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: when great men ſinne, many eyes are vpon them, and vſually iudgement is not farre off, where the rulers are naught.</p>
            <p>And now, brethren, when I conſider
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19236:27"/> how men liue by patterne, and not by precept, and how ready men are to giue an ill example; when I thinke of our late and generall loſſe, and of the hand of the Almighty vpon vs, in taking from vs a worthy lamp, I ſpeake of Sir <hi>Edward Lewkner,</hi> that not long ſince was Lord of this towne, and to the comfort of my ſoule and ioy of many Chriſtians, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented theſe aſſemblies, and ſhined like a light amongſt vs all, Oh when I thinke of this, then doe I wiſh that my head were full of waters, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile his death day and night; Oh then my ſoule is full of heauines, my bowells ſwell, and mine heart is euen turned within me, becauſe he that was wont to goe out and in before vs by a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, is taken away from vs, and makes his dwelling in the darke. Beloued in our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, ſpare me a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, while I ſhal propoſe (I was about to ſay a matchles) I dare ſay a worthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple before you for your imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let any in this aſſembly paſſe any raſh and vnaduiſed cenſure againſt me, for honouring a righteous man in his
<pb facs="tcp:19236:27"/> death, <hi>whoſe memoriall,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>ſhall bee bleſſed,</hi> Pro. 10. 7. For mine owne part, I cannot think it needeles in theſe times, when men liue by example, and not by rule, to propoſe a godly example before you for your imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For want of time, I will bound my ſpeech with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of theſe three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to ſpeake of his wiſedome; that he was a wiſe man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of his learning; that he was a learned man.</p>
            <p>Thirdly of his obedience; how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hee was to adde practiſe to his knowledge.</p>
            <p>And all that I ſhall ſpeake, the Lord of heauen knowes is truth, yea your ſelues can auouch it to be true. Indeed he liues lewdly in theſe dayes, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue one paraſite or other, to make a funeral Sermon in his praiſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: but for my ſelfe, if I ſpeake falſe, when I come downe from my pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, accuſe me before this Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and if I ſpeake but true, then giue glorie to God, and teſtifie with me.</p>
            <p>And firſt, I ſay, that he was <hi>truly wiſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">A wiſe man.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:19236:28"/> to diſcerne of things that differ, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent danger, &amp; to prouide againſt time to come. Firſt, to diſcerne and iudge of things: counting al things in this world, riches, pleaſures, beautie, as <hi>loſſe and dung, for the excellent knowledge ſake of Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3. 8. Secondly, as wiſe to preuent danger, rather willing to looſe any thing, then his owne ſoule. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as wiſe to prouide and lay vp <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in heauen,</hi> Luk. 12. 33. yea, <hi>his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation was in heauen,</hi> Phil. 3. 20. his affections mounting and aſpiring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. And whereas others of his ranke are wont to make this world their Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, one making a god of his belly, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other a goddeſſe of his <hi>Herodias;</hi> one hunting after honour, another after wealth; one conſuming all his precious time vpon dogges, another at the dice; one in an humour of cloaths, a ſecond in an humour of building; &amp; all drownd and drunken with the loue of vain plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, &amp;c. neglecting the good of their ſoules: you all knowe, that his delight was, like <hi>Ieremies,</hi> in the word of God, and that was <hi>the ioy and reioycing of his heart,</hi> Ier. 15. 16. His delight was like
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19236:28"/> 
               <hi>Dauids,</hi> in the houſe of God, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced when they ſaid, <hi>Come, let vs go to the houſe of the Lord,</hi> Pſalm. 122. 1. His ioy was like <hi>Pauls,</hi> in the <hi>free preaching of the Goſpell,</hi> Phil. 1. 18. His delight was in the companie of the Saints, and thoſe <hi>which are excellent,</hi> Pſalm. 16. 3. And as for that mad mirth, ſpoken of, Eccl. 2. 2. and the reioycing of the vngodly, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, Iob. 20. 5. might he not haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp <hi>Salomons</hi> words, <hi>I ſaid of laughter, thou art madde: and of ioy, what is it that thou doeſt?</hi> Eccl. 2. 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, was he not alſo <hi>learned,</hi> yea<note place="margin">2 Learned.</note> take the word in what ſenſe you pleaſe, in regard of humane or diuine learning? If I ſhould report how well skilled hee was in the tongues, in arts and ſciences, how cunning he was in the Scriptures, how powerfull hee was in diſputation, how ſtrongly he would refel a falſhood, how quicke he was of inuention, how ready to perceiue, &amp;c. I ſhould ſpeake no more then euerie man knowes alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, that were any whit of his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The truth is, that for ſtrength of wit, and naturall parts, as <hi>Iunius</hi> ſaid of that famous <hi>Vrſinus,</hi> I ſee not what was
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19236:29"/> wanting in him, that may be found in a man. Well, me thinks I may ſay of him with a little alteration of the words, as one writes of that bleſſed and worthy King, <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Aderant enim illi gratia, linguas enim multas callebat: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicam natalem, Latinam non expers (vt audio,) Grecae, &amp;c. non illi dialectica deerat, non naturalis Philoſophiae principia, &amp;c.</hi> &amp;<note place="margin">Cardanus.</note> as an other holy diuine wrote of the ſame Prince, the ſame may alſo bee ſaid of him; There wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in him no prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of wit, grauity of ſentence, ripenes of iudgment: and ouer and beſides theſe notable excellencies, and other great vertues in him, adde moreouer skill and knowledge of tongues, and other ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whereunto he ſeemed rather borne<note place="margin">Fox pag. 1547.</note> then brought vp.</p>
            <p>But had I <hi>Moſes</hi> learning, Act. 7. 22. were I as eloquent and mighty in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as <hi>Apollos,</hi> Act. 18. as full of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as a full veſſell is full of liquor, or the ſea ful of water; yet all were nothing<note place="margin">Thirdly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> obedience.</note> without obedience. Speake we therfore in the next place, of his practicke and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiue learning; of his ſanctification and righteouſneſſe: for as all ſinne is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19236:29"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vngodlineſſe,</hi> or <hi>vnrighteouſneſſe,</hi> Rom. 1. 18. ſo all the obedience that God requires of vs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the practiſe of theſe two things, 1. Holineſſe: 2. Righteouſneſſe. And whoſoeuer can finde in himſelfe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of both theſe, a care to ſerue the Lord in holineſſe, and to deale iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with men, is truely regenerate, Luk. 1. 73. Tit. 2. 12.</p>
            <p>Begin we then with ſanctification,<note place="margin">His holines.</note> which generally diſcouers it ſelfe by a godly life, 1. Pet. 1. 15. 16. Leu. 19. 2, 3. and more particularly by theſe fruits of ſanctification: 1. zeale for Gods glory: 2. frequency in prayer: 3. a care to draw others to God: 4. a care to honour Gods name: 5. care in the choiſe of godly ſeruants: 6. almeſ-deeds: 7. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe in grace: to name no more, all theſe are fruits, &amp; effects, and compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of holineſſe. See, Pſal. 66. 9. &amp; 119. 139. Act. 10. 1, 2. &amp;c. Hoſ. 6. 1. Ioh. 4. 28. Deut. 5. 11. and by all and euery one of theſe it plainely appeares, that this godly Gentleman was truely ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>For firſt, with the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> he<note place="margin">His zeale.</note>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:19236:30"/> was very <hi>zealous for the Lord of hoſts,</hi> 1. King. 19. 10. and like <hi>Dauid,</hi> accounted the wrongs done to God, as done to himſelfe, and <hi>hated the enemies of God,</hi> as his owne enemies, Pſal. 139. 21. and as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes, Pſal. 119. 48. <hi>I will ſpeak of thy teſtimonies before Kings, and will not be aſhamed:</hi> ſo let this be publiſhed to his eternall praiſe, that he was not aſhamed of the <hi>Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 1. 16. but whereſoeuer hee came, and amongſt whomſoeuer, ſuch was his zeale for God (that he could not like many tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizers, and time-ſeruers, and formall profeſſors, that walke in a middle tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and are neither hot nor cold) ſit ſtill and heare men plead for carnall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and ſay nothing; or heare the name of God blaſphemed, or preaching auiled, or profeſſion or profeſſors of the Goſpel ſpoken againſt, and neuer vnfold his lips, for God or his brethren: like many neuters, and night-profeſſors, Ioh. 3. 2. But as he was learned, &amp; knew how to ſpeake, ſo alſo he was zealous, and reſolute, and would not ſpare to ſpeake for Chriſt and for his Goſpel.<note place="margin">2 In prayer often.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, how holy was hee in his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19236:30"/> morning and euening ſacrifice, in his more priuate, and publike deuotions, twice a day reading the word, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his family: except ſome miniſter of the Goſpell (whom like another <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badiah</hi> he fedde at his owne table) were preſent to performe that duty: neither did he read his prayers vpon a booke, or tied himſelfe to ſtinted formes (which I condemne not in thoſe which haue not the hard gift of prayer, beeing like ſome man newly recouered of ſome ſickneſſe, that cannot goe except they be ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by another mans hand) but he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed freely according to the motion of Gods ſpirit: and how skilfully, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, there are many of his religious family to beare witneſſe. I remember what I read of <hi>Iob,</hi> Iob, 1. 5. when his ſonnes were banqueting in their houſes, <hi>Iob</hi> ſent, and ſanctified them, and offred vp burnt offerings for them: and the text addes moreouer, <hi>that he did it dayly and conſtantly, Thus did Iob euery day.</hi> The like may be ſaid of this worthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God, that he offered vp his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of praiſe and prayer to God, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day a morning and euening ſacrifice;
<pb facs="tcp:19236:31"/> and that ſo dayly and conſtantly, that his greateſt and waightieſt employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were none occaſion to him of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion: inſomuch that a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his diſſolution, beeing high ſhreiſe of this County, and taken vp with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great employments, yet was he ſo carefull and aſſiduous, euen in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt time of the Aſſiſes to begin and end the day with inuocation, that he would not enter vpon any buſines in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor giue ſleepe to his eyes in the euening, before he had called his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany together to ioyne with him in prayer. Neither was hee carefull alone to pray in his family more publikely, <hi>Oratio ſecretum poſtulat,</hi> nay his reines taught him in the night ſeaſon, (and as I am informed by thoſe from whome he could not altogither hide it) he ſet large times apart alſo for priuate praier. Some indeede there are that neuer inuoke Gods name, except before witneſſes. Firſt, they get them vpon the ſtage, and cauſe a trumpet to be blowne, and when they haue ſpectators enough, then they begin their deuotions. But <hi>Dauid praied in ſecret,</hi> 2. Sam. 12. 16. ſo did <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:19236:31"/> Act. 10. 9. ſo did <hi>Iacob,</hi> Gen. 32. 24. ſo did Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>avulſus eſt ab eijs qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ad iactum lapidis, &amp;c. Hee went a ſtones caſt from his diſciples, and kneeled downe, and prayed,</hi> Luk. 22. 41. Priuate prayer is an infallible ſymptom of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And now, brethren, I would I could ſpeak ſomething to mooue you in theſe vn-praying times: I haue called vpon you from Sabbath to Sabbath, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon after Sermon haue I prooued both the neceſſitie, power, and efficacie of praier, and for ought I heare all is as <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpilt vpon the ground,</hi> 2. Sam. 14. 14. I beſeech you al by the mercies of God, that this Gentlemans practiſe in this kind, may neuer out of your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: thinke of his care to ſanctifie his family, in offering vp his morning and euening ſacrifice, thinke of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and priuate conference with God, what ſecret intercourſe there was twixt God and his ſoule: I beſeech you again, I was about to charge you in the name of my God, to keep this example in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and that the thought of it may be as a ſpurre to prouoke you on
<pb facs="tcp:19236:32"/> to prayer: and if this example mooue you not, hearken then to <hi>Ieremies</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Powre out thy wrath vpon the heathen, and vpon thoſe familyes that call not vpon thy name,</hi> Ier. 10. 25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, how carefull was he to draw<note place="margin">Deſirous to draw others to God.</note> on others to God? I ſhall I confeſſe tel you ſtrange things, and yet no more then truth, that whereas other gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of his ſort, are wont to make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of mens ſoules; my meaning is to preſent idle &amp; vnworthy ſhepheards to their benefices for their owne aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and ſo fill the Church of God full of blind guides, fitter to be ouer-ſeene themſelues, then to ouer-ſee others; yet this gentleman, ſhall I ſay that he was a free Patron; nay, which is more ſtrange was he not ready to purchaſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuings with his owne ſiluer, and beſtow them <hi>gratis,</hi> as we ſay, vpon ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors as would be carefull of the flocke committed to their charge: and for mine owne particular I muſt needes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it with thankefulneſſe, that he freely and frankly made me the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy paſtor of this congregation, at his great coſt and expences. Againe,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19236:32"/> whereas others of his ranke, are wont to purloyne and rob the Church, and ſeeme to compound with the deuill, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mihi diuitias caeteri tolle tibi:</hi> giue me the profits of the Church, and take thou the ſoules of the people, and ſo place ſome vnworthy of their cures, while they make themſelues merry with the Lords portion, and ſpend it vpon dogs, hauks, and twenty to one of worſe matters; and then colour ouer all their the euery by calling of their benefices by the name of <hi>donatiues:</hi> this gentleman (whom I cannot eaſily paralel) whatſoeuer hee might doe by humane law, yet would he not make ſhip wracke of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for a little lucre: but like <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> to <hi>Melchizedecke, hee paied tithes of all,</hi> Gen. 13. 20. But alaſſe, our freind <hi>Lazarus</hi> is dead, his habitation is in the hill of <hi>Zion</hi> in the cittie of the liuing God: and behinde him there remaine, a number of Church-pyrats, that would not only rob the parſon, vicar, Church, Chappell, God, but would venture a voiage to hell for a little lucre.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, his ſanctification appeared further, by the care hee had to hallow
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19236:33"/> and honour Gods name: and this am I able to teſtifie for him, that ſince firſt I knew him, neuer did I heare one oth or<note place="margin">No ſwearer.</note> other great or ſmall fal from him, which ſpeaks not a little to his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation in theſe times, when our whole land is too full of blaſphemy, and thoſe deadly words ſpoken of, Eccleſ. 23. 11. are as common as ſtones in our ſtreetes: the time was when there were few ſwearers except men-ſwearers, but now our wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are not aſhamed to rap out oath after oath, to the diſhonour of God and his Sonne Chriſt: and as for too many of our gentry, (woe is me that I am borne to be a contentious man) come but within their threſholds to heare the maſter ſweare, and ſeruants ſweare (I quake and tremble to name their oaths, by the precious wounds of God, by Gods heart, by Chriſts blood, &amp;c.) a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would think himſelf entred into the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuburbs of hell; yea and with your fauour, many alſo that make ſcruple of greater, make little ſcruple of leſſer oaths, by their faith, troth, &amp;c. and ſuch a family as Sir <hi>Edward Lewkners</hi> (pardon me though I ſpeake bluntly) whether I
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19236:33"/> haue ſo often reſorted, and neuer hard one oath throughout the whole family, is hardly to be found in a country. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſe, my brethren, how can we chooſe but expect iudgement, when this feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſinne ſo raigneth, and rageth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs? <hi>I turned,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>and looked, and behold, a flying booke, the length of it 20. and the breadth of it 10. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits:</hi> and then it follows, <hi>Loe, this is the curſe that goeth ouer the whole earth, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that ſteales, and ſweares, ſhall bee cut off as well on this ſide as on that,</hi> Zach. 5. 1. 2. 3. and Zophon. 1. 4. <hi>I will,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>ſtretch out mine hand vpon Iudah, &amp;c. and I will cut off them that worſhip the hoaſt of heauen, and ſweare by the Lord and Malcham; and them that are turnd backe from the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, how cautelous was he in the choice of his houſehold ſeruants, a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table teſtimony of a man truely ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: <hi>there ſhall not dwell a wicked perſon in mine houſe,</hi> Pſal. 106. All his care was to haue ſeruants fearing God vnder his roofe, ruffians, ſwaggerers, toſpots, prophane <hi>Eſaus,</hi> blaſphemous <hi>Rabſaches</hi> were hatefull to him; and which is very
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19236:34"/> memorable during the time of his ſhrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualdry, and hauing (if I miſtake not the number) neere vpon ſixty wearing his liuery, yet could I neuer heare of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny outragious or inordinate ſwearers or drunkards amongſt the number. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I a little muſe at many gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, yea and of ſome that would make a ſhew of the beſt things, that yet enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine royſters, and riotous perſons within their doors; and when we preach againſt it, reply for themſelues, that good ſeruants are not to be found in an whole country. To which I anſwer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that though godly ſeruants are as thin ſowne as godly maſters, yet ſome there are to be found, elſe God forbid. And ſecondly, let no man take offence againſt me for ſpeaking truth; for mine owne part I am of this opinion, that it were better for gentlemen to doe any office themſelues, then to entertaine one leude ſeruant into their houſes: for one godleſſe wretch in an houſe, is like <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> in the ſhippe, and brings vengeance vpon all the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, his holines appeared further, by his almes-deeds: ſo the <hi>ſpirit</hi> ſaith of<note place="margin">His almes.</note>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:19236:34"/> 
               <hi>Cornelius,</hi> that he was a <hi>deuout man,</hi> and how doth he prooue it? <hi>Hee gaue much almes, and prayed much,</hi> Acts. 10. verſ. 2. The like may I ſay of our kinde Lord and freind deceaſed; he was a <hi>deuoute man:</hi> and thus I prooue it; hee prayed much, and beſides he was full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Your ſelues can beare me record, how many of your poor people he cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the ſleeces of his ſheepe, and what his cuſtome was, (<hi>viz.</hi>) for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery<note place="margin">Laſt yeare beeing 32. yeares old, he cloathed 32. poore people.</note> yeare of his life, to cloath one of your poore and naked ones. Some may happily wonder at ſo great expence from one man, and it may be ſome haue ſaid to him as <hi>Iudas</hi> did; <hi>Ad quid perditio haec?</hi> what needes all this this waſte? is it not enough to cloath the poore of your owne towne? The money ſpent in apparelling ſo many poore, would buy a great deale of ſoft raiment for your owne family: Charity muſt beginne at home: In time this courſe will ſucke your coffers too much. Though I accuſe none, no nor ſuſpect any, yet is it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable enough, that ſome might open their mouths to this effect. Chriſt neuer did good work but ſome or other were
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19236:35"/> offended. Yea, but may ſome ſay, the hungry muſt be fed as well as the naked cloathed: our Sauiour ſaith, not onely, <hi>Hee that hath two coates, let him giue to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 3. 11.</note> 
               <hi>him that hath none:</hi> but he addes moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, <hi>and he that hath meat, let him doe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe:</hi> did he therfore feed the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gry? Yes verily, and gaue a portion to <hi>ſeauen,</hi> and alſo to <hi>eight,</hi> Eccleſ. 11. 1. witneſſe the great company of Orphans, widdowes, and fatherleſſe children that weekely and dayly ſought and found releife at his gates: and which is worthy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance in theſe dayes, when ſome like <hi>Abſolom</hi> build Pyramides to keep their names from obliuion, 2. Sam. 18. 18. and others like <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> mount vp their turrets of <hi>Babell,</hi> Dan. 4. 33. for vaine oſtentation, till they haue vtterly diſabled themſelues, for all workes of charity; This gentleman (at the name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of whom mine heart bleeds afreſh within me) his buildings were for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vſes: and it is well knowne to you which heare me this day, that he reared vp one building neer his own houſ, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed it with a large table to the onely vſe and releefe of the poore, that thrice
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19236:35"/> a weeke reſorted thither, and were li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally prouided for, to his great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences. Inſomuch that he might haue pleaded for himſelfe as <hi>Iob</hi> did; If I haue reſtrained the poore of his deſire, or haue cauſed the eyes of the widowe to faile; if I haue eaten my morſells alone, and the fatherleſſe hath not eaten there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; if I haue ſeene any periſh for want of cloathing; if I haue lift vp mine hand againſt the fatherleſſe, then let mine arme fall from my ſhoulder, yea let it be broken from the bone. Iob. 31. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seauenthly and laſtly, his <hi>holineſſe</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared by his continuall progreſſe in grace. For ſo ſaith God, <hi>They which wait vpon the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength, they ſhall lift vp their wings as the eagles, they ſhall runne and not be wearie, they ſhall walke and not faint,</hi> Iſa. 40. ver. 31. And whereas the vngodly may fitly be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> that bent their bowes, and made a ſhewe as though they would fight, but <hi>turned back in the day of battell,</hi> Pſal. 78. 9. or rather to men in a conſumption, that conſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by little and little, vntill they are buried in the earth: though hypocrites
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19236:36"/> decline and grow worſe and worſe, yet now I ſpeake of one, of whome I may ſay, as it was ſaid of the Church of <hi>Thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atira,</hi> that <hi>his workes were more at the laſt, then at the firſt,</hi> Reu. 2. 19. or as it was ſaid of <hi>Ruth,</hi> the ſame alſo may be ſaide of him, that he ſhewed <hi>more good at the latter end, then at the beginning,</hi> Ruth. 3. 19. more heauenly minded, more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for Gods honour, more carefull to draw others to God, more often in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, more cautelous in the choiſe of his houſhold-ſeruants, fuller of good works and almeſ-deeds, and euery way more fruitfull (though neuer barren) at the laſt then at the firſt: all his houſhold-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants perceiued as much: and for mine owne part, I neuer reſorted to the houſe, but me thoughts I ſaw a ſenſible growth in goodneſſe. And now, beloued, ſince a godly life in generall, and the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars named, of zeale, frequencie in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp;c. be infallible notes of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though I ſay nothing of his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, beeing as <hi>humble as the child new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weaned,</hi> Pſal. 131. 2. of his care to hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and ſanctifie the Lords Sabbaths, both he and his houſhold: of his care to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19236:36"/> teach and inſtruct his family; yet haue I ſpoken ſufficient for the probation of his holineſſe.</p>
            <p>I might now ſpeake as largely of his<note place="margin">2. His righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</note> righteouſneſſe, but that time commands me to take my worke out of the loome. Yet thus much I will be bold to ſpeake, and promiſe before this audience, in the words of <hi>Samuel</hi> to the people, 1. Sam. 12. 3. <hi>Whoſe oxe hath he taken? or whoſe aſſe hath he taken? to whom hath he done wrong? or whom hath hee hurt? or at whoſe hands hath hee taken a bribe?</hi> and if he hath it ſhall be reſtored. But I cannot ſtand to ſpeake of theſe things, neither of his godly death, wherein alſo I might bee copious. But dead hee is, his bodie I meane is dead; as for his ſpirit, that liues in the city of the liuing God, amongſt millions and myrriads of heauenly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, in the company and Chuch of thoſe firſt begotten, which are gathered into an heauenly, with the Iudge of all fleſh, in the newe Ieruſalem, whoſe gates are pearle, whoſe ſtreetes gold, whoſe wals are precious ſtones, where quires of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the Cherubims and the holy Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phims, ſing <hi>Halaluiah, Hoſanna,</hi> to God
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19236:37"/> on high; and there he ſhines and ſhall ſhine, like the brightneſſe of the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and gliſter like the ſtarres for euer and euer: while we remaine vpon the troublous ſea of this world to lament his loſſe; yea, who can ſufficiently la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it?</p>
            <p>How can his godly Lady lament e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, for the loſſe of ſo kind and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an husband, that loued and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred her as his owne ſoule.</p>
            <p>How can his young children lament enough, when they ſhall come to years of diſcretion, and find themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued of ſo carefull and louing a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>How can his ſeruants lament enough for the loſſe of ſo religious a Maſter, that was wont to goe out and in before them by a godly example, and was ſo diligent to teach and inſtruct them in the way of godlines.</p>
            <p>How can the learned and louers of learning lament enough, ſince hee is gone, that like that famous king of <hi>Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> beeing asked whether he had rather<note place="margin">Robert, King of Sicil.</note> forſake the companie of certain learned men about him, or his Kingdome; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19236:37"/> his kingdome, rather then his learning, or learned tutors: ſince hee is gone that preferred learning before his great poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>How can the deſpiſed Miniſters of the word lament enough, now that they are counted the skumme of the world, and refuſe of the people, and he is fallen that accounted of them, as the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of God, and the diſpenſers of the myſteries of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>How can the profeſſors of the Goſpel mourne enough, ſince he is taken away that loued the verie name of a diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>And all the poore and needy in the towne round about, that are hungrie, harbourleſſe, and want cloathing, how can they lament enough, ſince he is dead that was wont to giue them meat in due ſeaſon; and whileſt he liued, deliuered the poore that cryed, and the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and him that had none to helpe him; <hi>that was an eie to the blinde, a foote to the lame, and a father to the poore,</hi> Iob 29. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>And for my part would I could weep ſhowres of teares with <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> or
<pb facs="tcp:19236:38"/> floods of teares with <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> yea day and night with <hi>Ieremie,</hi> ſince I haue loſt, what is hardly found, a true, a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friend. Since he is gone, whoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall (conſider his young yeares, his great eſtate, his gifts both of grace and nature) will hardly be paraleld. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I haue ſpoken in his iuſt prayſe, but alaſſe, I haue but touched the hony, like <hi>Ionathan,</hi> with the tip of my rod, 1. Sam. 14. 43. and lapt with <hi>Gideons</hi> ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; my meaning is, that I haue not ſpoken according to halfe his worth. I know indeed that loue is mighty as wine, and ſtrong as death, and affection may carry mee too farre; happily I may commend him too much, that it may be I loued too much; but God knowes, that I euer hated a paraſite from my childehood; and the Lord the ſeer and ſearcher of all hearts knowes it, that I haue not ſpoken one word with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to flatter any perſon liuing, by commending him that is dead. And yet notwithſtanding, ſince the examples both of the liuing and dead, doe farre more mooue then precepts, I hope it will not be altogether vnprofitable to
<pb facs="tcp:19236:38"/> propoſe a godly example before you, though for his good workes, (I muſt needs ſay what I thinke) and ſay as the Queene of the South ſaid of the glorie and wiſedome of <hi>Salomon,</hi> that <hi>the one halfe hath not beene told you.</hi> We that liue ſo much by patterne, would God we would ſet this patterne before our eies, and learne by his example to labour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heauenly wiſedome, and true lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſtirre vp our ſelues to ſerue God in holineſſe and righteouſnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him all our dayes; yea, and to enter vpon this gracious courſe moſt ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. It is not long ſince this gentleman beeing but young, about 32. yeares of age, it is not long ſince that he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, and in liking as we are, not long ſince that he ſat where we ſit, and heard where we heare, and praied where we pray, and had we not need then to looke about vs? If <hi>Abell</hi> die, muſt not <hi>Cain</hi> much more: If <hi>Iſaac</hi> die, muſt not <hi>Iſmael</hi> much more: If <hi>Simon Peter</hi> die, muſt not <hi>Simon Magus</hi> much more? if holy, religious, righteous <hi>Sir Edward Lewknor</hi> die before he ſee 33. yeares, why ſhould we dreame of any long continuance? If <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
